You can build twenty-fifth while.
Welcome to build twenty fifteen armory townsend and
lead program manager on the windows inputs platform team and say we
...about...platform how take full advantage of it in your apps.
...been...you to fill out a session evaluation there are
prices so please do that another slide...the talk has...can scan.
...cover for
brought areas today the first is universal windows platform and what is the promising
...to developers and how that relates to inputs we'll talk next about the
input platform at a high-level and talk about the various layers
of the platform stack and what's available to you then
...jump into some code will get our hands dirty will look at some examples
...pointers to other interesting sessions and other resources for you?
So, what is the universal windows platform and what exactly is
it promising developers...two important aspects the first aspect is that the same
platforms available...on all devices running windows down and then as was
mentioned the keynote this morning the second important aspect is largely due to our windows
as a service work...hundreds of millions of machines out there running one-in-ten
you can target so put those two things together and you have a huge
...market you can very easily target with your apps?
So, I really like the slide from the keynote one of the things is great and unique about windows is the breadth of
hardware we support there's a huge number of form factors
devices that only run windows from little internet of things devices to
...surface hub holographic devices...columns but from
...point of view that means there's a lot of inputs you to think about there's touch
...phones and tablets and
...and surface hub there's...many of the same devices
...game controllers there's holographic input me talk about mouse and keyboard.
how does the input platform help you...the input platforms promises similar to universal windows,
windows platforms promise and the same input platforms available to on all
of these devices but the corollary that is there's a lot of different inputs that
your apple be exposed to as it runs on that breath hardware
are promise is the input platform makes it easy to handle all these inputs and...
you build the applicant vision all ad I think the apps that will do best on the store will be the apps
that best handle that breadth of hardware that they'll end up running on it's an easy way to differentiate your
app from others?
...quick demo.
Let's see the universal platform in action here.
So, I will start actually with the desktop
Launch one note here this is the universal at version one of the office teams
...a great job building universe
...I think you saw earlier today the excel and powerpoint versions of this is the one
up and input works is you'd expect here I can use the
mouse I can create a new page and my notes I can type with...
keyboard build demo twenty fifteen this is.
Text I entered on desktop.
You can use touch if I have a
pen on my surface I can inc address smiley face.
So, input works.
Very much as you'd expect here but this is universal
lap so I can also.
Run it on the phone.
So, I've got the same version of one note here on the phone I don't think you need to see my
to do list of you can see that it's...to the page we now have that
page we just created over here on the desktop touch works is using a as use can
expect you can pan you consumer content...the
...rendering here I can.
Double tap syntax I...enter text...but also hooked up a bluetooth
mouse and keyboard let me move that text backer hit tab along so I can
use the mouse and I can select here on the phone.
...new text some entering...the farm using the mouse so universal windows platform
what's you run your app across all these devices the input platforms the
...platform available in both places here the one
...didn't write any special code for desktop it write a special code for
...code running a and
as part of this work we brought a bunch of new inputs to devices that didn't happen before.
Hand as you saw this morning keynote adding a bluetooth keyboard and
mouse to a phone is the first step and participating that continuum experience so-if
identify fun connected it to a display via html by or mirror
cast I can get a pc like experience desktop like experience...just my phone.
What xbox?
Some of you is developers the audience may be thinking yourself I know
how to write a tablet app I know how to write a phone app what happens when that...goes to an xbox what I do
their or vice...on building a game I know exactly what I want to with
comptroller but I don't know-how that's going to translate when I bring it back to a pc or maybe something like
a phone or tablet the universal windows platform this fall will bring the xbox
schematic peons to the platform available for
your across devices so I think a lot of you probably seen xbox one
comptroller and, you used with xbox but how many of you seen a xbox one
controller on a desktop and universal lap.
So, we took a really simple sample I think many of you...this before this is the direct
...first-person shooter samples been around for a while we converted it to be a universal windows
app...five minutes we added...support and suddenly you have an
application ditch will work great on your xbox or create on your pc and,
it's really are universal platform that's going to make handling
comptroller really easily really easy and all your apps.
...platform so the
input platform has three we typically think about it and three layers the
...layer is kind of what you get for free
frameworks controls have a bunch of built-in support whether it's things like input events the
frameworks generate for-you for controls state ticker slider text box
...there's a bunch of new controls...as well as much
of built-in stuff you get for free the next slayer is really, you know,
if you need more powered flexibility maybe you're building some custom control that's when he
stepped down and use api...like pointer pointer device gesture recognizer things in that
family...give you a lot more our and flexibility
and finally if you need ultimate our you can go down to core input this is about as close to the
metals you can get...talk about this towards the end of the talk but this is where you go if
...other layers aren't giving you exactly the control our flexibility and need.
So, we'll talk about each layer interned I'll start with frameworks controls the frameworks offer
which controls and, the controls all have support for inputs
are built into them already so you can use something like a button with touch with...with
...keyboard all this works is you'd expect if you stick to the built-in controls the frameworks
provider apps just going to work across that broad spectrum of hardware whether
you're running on a phone or on a surface hub your apple just work.
...looking at some code here are pull visual studio up and we'll do a quick.
Example.
Of what you get...controls.
...so,...sample here.
I have a really simple sample...on a second it's just
adding three basic controls to my app we've got a button we've got a
...a text box I pick these because a show something interesting about input the
button I can use the mouse always got hooked up to do is change the background
of the application I can click on with the mouse I can use pen and
tap on I can use touch and tap on and if it's got focus I can use
the keyboard and cycle through it so all of these controls right out-of-the-box
...support the inputs you're going to see across are broad spectrum of hardware.
The next control here.
The...hard-to-read...enslavement...the next control here
is a slider and sliders also pretty simple control you can see I move it
...shows me the value and so-call out ...interact with touch the
call out moves sliders a good way to demonstrate that we thought about the interesting aspects of each
input and we've customize the controls to be optimized for those inputs if we had the
...out with the value in the same place we do for mouse you wouldn't go see it with your finger,
you know, your fingers to large
...you wouldn't see it another thing that's interesting about the slider is that
it uses capture so I can grab the phone here but I can also move my finger off and still
interact with it part of the reason this works is the slider when you successful
...the thumb sets capturing all future input goes to the phone I'll talk about that more and
one of our later examples but it's a helpful tool for you and your building controls.
And, finally we got a text box here text box is built on scroll viewer I'll talk more about school here
...a second it's behaves as you'd expect with touch we've got feedback when you get to the
andof content...can you
know, select text and...type with the keyboard.
I can use...there, for example, but, we've also,
... this is another control where we've done some interesting differences between the inputs with
mouse you have the traditional...selection model but if I use touch,
for example,you get the grip...you can grab the
...to changer selection so there's a slightly different selection model for touch so for each of our
controls we not only support the impacts that you can expect to see across all the devices
in the broad windows harder spectrum we thought about...the right behavior for all these controls.
Let's look at the sample for this.
The interesting...animal.
Is these three?
...have a button that we're putting in there we have a slider control...text box there's
nothing particularly interesting we're doing here if we look at the backing csharp.
Other than.
Just spinning in a for...adding syntax...the text box there really isn't a lot
were doing the button has some code you just randomly set of background color but this is, you know,
this is all functionality get other box we haven't written a bunch of code for penn, for example, make-work...
scenes but speaking of penn what's ad inc supports really quickly to
our application and uncommon some code here and adding canvas
so in canvas is one of the new controls were offering and ten it adds...to
...lap the canvas will expand...parent tolerances so I've just
put it in a grid here and given it a heighten width so it doesn't take up the entiresurface of the sample.
And, in our backing csharp.
Some comments and code the default behavior
...canvas is that it collects...from penn but I want to also collect
...so I can set on the in canvases
in presenter the input devices types property I can set it to capture not just
...but also touch.
So, let's compile run that and I'll show you what you get within canvas.
And, go back to our control sample and now we
...canvas at the bottom I can use my pen and I can...and,
you get such a beautiful and here I can use touch
I can include as well you can turn on mao sinking if you want
to so in canvas gives you a lot of functionality the box it's really easy to add your application
...features around beautiful fining can cleaning it up so it's not just, you know,
raw points connected with straight lines there is reco features
you can get access to it supports input from a variety of different
input types like mouse and, pen
and touch and we have a couple talks will go into much more depth about inc that you should see tomorrow.
Samoa...dec here.
So, there's lots of you...for free with the frameworks but sometimes you need more than what they give you
an...classes of things usually...here for the first is
...controls are customizable I'll talk about scroll...or school...important control but it's...
as an example because it also offers a lot of customization and also talk about
the input events and the gesture events you can get from the frameworks and what you can do with those?
So, scroll viewer is an interesting control we looked at
the top apps on the store and eighty percent of them
...scroll viewers...apron of the sam lapses a scroll viewer in their
code somewhere which is really high number and when you consider scroll
...also powers a number of other controls like grid view unless you
...foot view and text box when you expanse that entire family of controls either user
...powered by...the number jump to ninety percent of the top...are using it somewhere in their
code which is which is huge the remaining ten percent are things like games or other
apps don't even use this animal controls so basically all of the top
sam lapse that are using the controls using scroll viewer and one way shape or form so it's definitely a powerful
...certainly popular part of the reasons popular is
panning is such a core part of our interaction language...you're on a phone you
...small-screen you panther content a lot of our controls like pivot
and hub are built on panning behaviors
...here gets used in a lot of places and, it's
...just offers you a way to have a lot of content
and a small space in your app and sort of panned through...right but you can also do other things you can turn
on support presume you can turn inertia on or off
other snap points so you can if you have...on and somebody pans within a
...generator...points will ensure that you and illogical boundary and content
...so things like rails and sat points resume and other things like that you can turn on as well?
So, let's look a little bit of code here and a sample using scroll viewer.
So, we have a real simple sample here there's a bunch of toggle goals and drop down
that control some behaviors behind-the-scenes but the...itself is this set
of rectangles we've just stuffed a stack panel...the school viewer...stockpile has a bunch of racks and the
...of different colors so I can panned through these by default you can see that
...get inertia panning for free I haven't I haven't touched anything here yet I notice
...scroll bar on the side the scroll
bar with touch since panning such an easy thing to do with touch we don't really expected use
escobar scroll bars really more of just a visual telling you where you are in your content but,
if I use mouse and bring it over here you'll see that we get a traditional scroll bar
...another example of how we sort of
optimize the controls for each of the inputs you might be interacting with them.
I can do things here like turnoff
...so if I turn off inertia obviously it doesn't have inertial
and I pam I can turn on zoom and you can do
some like zoom out on the stack panel and see all...here we
...way back in if we want all this is powered by the great pan zoom
behavior you get from direct manipulation behind-the-scenes the frameworks take care of this for you.
So, you can also turn on snap points so when I panda content
it doesn't necessarily snap to any content boundary but,
if I turn on optional snap points when I pan you'll see that we
adjust inertia curve to ensure that you always land right on the edge of
well most of the time you land on the edge of a content boundary the optional ones don't force you
to...if it would be too much of change like, for example, when I panned like that it's not going to
snap made anything but if we have a little more velocity it makes it pretty easy to just tweak the curve a little bit
and sure you and on a logical content boundary if you move to something like mandatory snot
points I can't leave the stack panel here and have it not
...snap to a content boundary so mandatory will force you to
...something this is really good for control like...view like if you have a control where
...flipping through photos you probably don't want to leave the user...a space where about half of one for
...and half another that'd be great place to use mandatory snap points but if
you're building something like excel or maybe a list...you've got a list of
...maybe it's not quite as important that you always snap to a content boundary could
...optional...points and then it would look very natural for the user when it does snap?
So, let's look at the code here.
So, the demo for this is real simple ...just look at the code so when we
toggle inertia all we're doing behind-the-scenes with the school fewer
is toggle in this property is scroll inertia enabled real simple to turn
inertia on often your...there's also a zoom inertia so maybe you have a map and
it's panel in two dimensions you can zoom monitors well maybe you want or
...resume there and let users, you know,
maybe on smaller...what's kind of a pain to sort of repeatedly zoom you could turn
...should make it easier to make large...zoom factor when.
Resuming the toggle
...turn it on off just changes the zoom mode property so there's a scene am zoom...you can
...to enabled disabled really straightforward.
Snap points.
We have a little switch statement down here that looks at whatever the value of the drop down
as...the vertical snap point type.
There's a number of properties for
...points there's a whole set of properties for horizontal snot points as a whole set of properties for vertical
...points you can do things like set the type there's mandatory this optional you can turn
them off there are properties for alignment
thank you probably noticed in the sample it was always snapping to the top of the
racks you can have it snap to the bottom of your elements for the center of your elements if you want you
can change the alignment there's also...points that you can control and other things you can sudden
in school...as well...rails other behaviors that are customizable rails
are useful for cases maybe you've got some to dependable content but most of the time
users panned vertically with it and you want to clean-up sort of sloppy
vertical pans into something that really is access aligned that's a great place to turn on rails so
...viewers really customizable and gives you a lot of options...really easy to
use is really just changing a couple properties on it and sticking...content and it and you get, you know,
that really great zoom and,...experience you...with windows.
Other than customizing events
...patrols the other thing that you can do with the frameworks pretty easily is
respond input events and...a couple classes of these
...raw planar events I think a lot of you're familiar with planar they
let you do things like telephone planar comes down on ui element and sandler
...web app and you could use it maybe building
...some custom control that has button like feedback you could use the pointer down and,
up events to simulate press feedback on the button there's also enter and exit events that would let
you simulate things like hover so if you want
...bring a mouse or a pen over a control
...have some hover feedback...tool to pops up you can do that with the pointer events
...also gesture events and...provides us relatively rich
ones web apps and html providepretty standard set
to and with these you can respond to a lot of the standard gestures ec and windows
...double tap have a right click event we'll talk about a second.
Look, at a couple of these an action.
...run the sample again and show you.
Are code here so again another super simple sample from this animal point of view we've
got four racks and each of them handles different events so this top most
...listens for poynter preston released events...changing the color
on it again these events are fired for all the inputs that we care about
so touch mouse I can use penn here and sugar all the same...using the penn
I can hover over this control and you can see that I get enter and exit a
...get the same thing with the mouse you can tap or double
tap on this one and we're listening to some basic gesture events and
thenthis bottom control listens to the right tap event we should talk about right
tap...kind of a meta event brings together all the things that are logically
right click across all of the inputs so for a mouse...click as a
...click for...person...or...high-touch
...supports two ways of generating right cliques you can...hold with the panned just...touch or even hold the
barrel button...if your...has apparel button so...a lot of ways to get write collects
...to make it easy for use a developer to just have a single handler for these things and the
input subsystem behind-the-scenes takes care of recognizing what the input was what the
...data flying from that input was...deciding if it's a right click...
event for you so very simple...the code here?
So, we set up our sample.
She can get rid of...what...
We...sample with a couple...handlers the first pair are the preston released chandler see-saw
at first box...pointer comes down or up those events get triggered the next pair are entering
exits when a pointer comes over some content you'll see these.
For the gesture hammers were listening to...double tap right tap which is that
meta event that sort of roles all the right click events together and holding we'll talk about holding
a second most of the handlers in the sample are real simple to just changing the background color
of direct that they were in so not much to talk about there but
when we get down to holding its own marketing holding is an event that has a couple different states so if you're doing
...with touch...basically three things that can happen
you figure comes down if you wait long enough you eventually get a holdings start
we don't want slow taps or the user just brushes the screen to structuring
...holds the sometime threshold after pass before.
Will allow you to be a person hold state once you've crossed the holding state then
one or two things can happen...successfully complete the...holder you could drag away and, then the
whole gets canceled so in the whole cancel case you'd see a holed cancelevent
come in the...state would behold canceled or in the case where they...
successfully holding status completed if we go back to the app and I
...hold you can see that after a person hold on it we get the
holed start events and we update the text...the color for holding and if I drag away we got a whole
cancelled...get personal if I do successfully person
...touch you'll see that it generates both a holed complete...right...
event immediately afterwards and the right...comes in so fast you can't see the...saying that
...completed their so handling these basic input events is really simple as well?
So, what happens when you need a little more our flexibility if what's built
into the frameworks isn't what you need where do you go so?
This is
...of second layer and platform...I talk about these are sort of lower-level api to
give you more control over the raw data and gesture detection
and other things like that so these are really good for building custom controls or experience
...go beyond what you get for free.
So, first thing to talk about our the...api the pointer api is I think most of you have use
these before they abstract touch and...mouse together all of our pointing types may
be future inputs into one coherent api surface
that api surface makes it really easy for you to get common properties that all of these
pointer type share things like the position of...pointer the idea of a
pointer a handle back to the device the type of it but you can also if you want to
you can go and grab off the property bag on the planar you can get input specific
typed data so...have things like pressure you can figure out how hard the
users pressing something like touch has a contact
...we know the bounding box around the fingers you can make some decisions based on the contact
wrecked mouse has buttons and we'll state and things
like that so pointers relation api
will show you this I don't know-how many of you follow web standard discussions but
wthree-c just ratified...web version of planar as a new standard so we're
super excited about that we worked with firefox google a bunch of folks in the web community
to iterate on the standard make it better over the last year-and-a-half and just two months ago
...accepted as a standard so we're very excited about that firefox
has a implementation right now google's working implantation obviously ie and
...both have implementations of the new pointer standard to
...web apps or your webpages directly.
So, what's the code.
And,...see pointers expression in.
The universe...
So,...should sorry.
Our sample here there's a couple things so we set up a couple
dictionaries basically to track.
The contacts andlet me show you the sample for talk about code.
So, we...sample here that.
Does a couple things when I put any pointer down it basically gives us debug spew about the
pointer you can see in the black section of the top a bunch of common data if I
put a touchdown you can see that the common data remains the same
we're showing you id position contact...other common properties but,
then in different colors below you can see some input
type specific data so if I go back to mouse it shows us the button state right now pulling
down the left button if I hold on the right button...can see that here
...like touch you can see that the id for all these contacts are
different we can track all of these things we talked before about contact...so I put my
fun down and if my...mostly perpendicular to the screen you can see that
direct is you know, more or less square right it's sort of, you know,
ninety by seventy profess start flattening my thumb ouch?
You can see you should see.
That the width.
Sorry the height gets larger
so sometimes hardware detects contact...some doesn't when I
single-point api stews you can tell if the hardware is give you that information very easily you
can query and say hey do supports contact direct you can find out for things like
penn we have a bunch of button state so I can press the barrow button I can press
the racer and I can work with pressure here so I can max out the pressure
or press very lightly.
So, if you want to get to that rich input specific data like maybe
you're one node and you want to do something special with panned where you vary the thickness of your
...you can get to that data and make those kinds of decisions
and your app so now let's look at the code.
...real simple it's just a blank page behind-the-scenes we have a couple
dictionaries for tracking those ui pops that we create but,
the real magic is listening to these pointer events
...for point oppressed move to released and
...changes and then the handles for these do a little bit of
work like tracking the point but they really just create those property pops
...you saw following the different events so for
point oppressed we create the property pop up here for poynter move we
for...released we clean-up after ourselves what does it look like getting those property
...what we do two things we wonget the
...properties and then we also check if there's device specific properties for that
input type common properties are relatively easy to get these are all the
sort of first-class properties hanging off the pointer...there's things like
pointer id there's a point that represents the position you can get the x and y
...you can get whether it's in contact or not you can check the...you can get a handle back to the
pointer device and do things with the device...as a number of things all
...share and we point some of out here and then we look at
the type of the...so checking...it...as
...touch and then we go and look for some property specific to those so
in mouse, for example, the first thing we do is get the property bag so each pointer
points has a properties property that is a property bag and it has all the rich
type specific data in it so the grab that property bag and then
from it we can get things like the button states whether somebody's generating a mouse
...if we look at hatch touch?
You can see we can get things like the contact racks the contact tight.
There's some to models for working with the stuff one is you can ask the hardware
...support pressure because, you know, theoretically
attach device could support pressure doesn't have to be a pen so you could ask the hardware and say
do you support share pressure whatever property alternatively all
these properties sort of have smart defaults to and you can just use pressure directly
...application and if it's a input that doesn't support it you'll get some default value like
a median pressure or if you want to use contact wrecked and your
app even just code against it and the contact will be zero for hardware doesn't support it and it will
have some nonzero value for hardware that does support so a lot of these properties are smart
behind-the-scenes and make it easy says...a bunch of if this property exist...my hardware do xyz.
So, pointers relatively simple to work with.
...players good for things like building a paint apple they problem user
...king api for that maybe you're building custom control, you know,
if you're if you're rebuilding button for some reason you use raw pointer events but
a lot of cases you want gestures right if you're trying to rebuild something like scroll of your you'd want to detect
...launched zooms.
Maybe you have some nip your bowl object in your application like a
pain that somebody can dragged down from the edge of the application or something like that
those are good places to use things like gesture recognizer just recognizer provides
you a common reusable way of getting to the systems gesture detection and
...detects number of things like taps and holds manipulations
other gestures but it gives you the same inertia curves that you see also in the system
has the same thresholds for tap and double tap it knows how to generate a
write taped event from all the different inputs so if you want to handle right click you don't need
to know build for different gesture detection things for the two ways...does it the way
...mouse doesn't...a lot of built-in system functionality there that's reusable for you a couple
...cases what makes...to use it maybe you're not using a framework maybe you're building a game where
your app is built directly on top...car window and using direct...to do
your rendering those are cases where you have to go rajesh recognizer another more complex
case might be something like I have a bunch of gesture recognizers and they're all
configured differently and I want to pass input to all of them see what the outputs look like and
then make some decision based on what that
output looks like that might be a case where you have to go to gesture recognizer.
Let's take a look at some of the code.
And, actually before we look at the code let's talk about what zambia gives you
hear so we'll services annals sample.
This is real simple we've got some ui that toggle
...and basically have a...that we can manipulate here so we've set it up to
allow translation and rotation it's got some inertial I can
for off-screen and, we've also done some things to control how gesture detection
works here we can constrain the element...
Move on one access you can see here with locked
the x axis I can lock it to the y axis as well or have it
...for two-d manipulate ball and,
this is all built on stuff that example gives you today so let's look at the code for that
and then we'll take a look at just recognizer how to build the same experience with that?
So, we're talking about the input events available to the in something example you can listen
to more than just happen double tap and right click that we showed the first example you
...listen to richer gesture events like manipulations so that's what we
fucked up here the sample simple just a
...and we're going to set a couple handlers on it so we do
some initialization we set up our transforms.
But, then.
We go and listen to for different manipulation events
so manipulation started fires when you start a...zoom or rotator something like
that manipulation delta fires during the progression of your events while the
users panning you're going to get started and...a bunch of deltas...tracking how far they've moved you have
...completed when all the fingers come up in the manipulation...
inertia design you can also see...manipulation inertia starting event that tells you that...begun.
then manipulate me here is just the name of our ...and the sample.
Ui elements and sample have a manipulation
mode property on them and here we're configuring it to allow for translation
...the x axis translation the y axis and rotation and we set
up inertia for both of these things so we just or all those together and stick it in this manipulation
mode and now you will start getting manipulation events when you interact with
that ui element so relatively simple the transform stuff that we
set up we initially set...to the identity transform but as we listen
to those manipulation events will be updating the transform the
...transform on that...general start showing up and handling input
in different spots based on the transform so manipulation started?
We're just changing the color of the...to let, you know, you're interacting with it if you remember the sample turns blue when you
...a lot of the real work happens and manipulation delta.
the first thing we do is we save the old transform because what we get
manipulation delta is the new components for
translations scale changes and rotation changes it's not accumulative one
there is a cumulative event that you can get to but are just handling
deltas here so the first-order businesses to calculate the center of
that interaction if we go back to the sample for a second, you know,
I don't always want to just rotate around the center of the...sometimes on a rotate around a
point like if I grab a corner...I want to build...have that sort of natural interaction file
and rotate...and rotating around this corner and not the center of
the element so we figure out what the center of
the manipulation event that's coming to us is we save that and then we take the
delta coming off...and apply it to our rotation component of our transform
and we take the x and y translation of events the information and them and apply
...xy translation...delta transform this then gets applied to the
...and suddenly example now...new position when inertia starts and when
...completes...change the color again so real simple handlers there so,
the meat of what's happening here and sample is pretty
straightforward you set manipulation mode on the ui element the want to build interact with, you know, whether it's that
...moving around or maybe of a pain that you want pull down you it's just
...why translation or something like that and then you add some of
...you start getting your events and you can calculate a new transformed apply to
that element if we want to look at how we did things like
...to a specific access were just x sorry...your translation
in the y axis...x axis of I want to lock it to the horizontal axis we
...translation why really straightforward you can just change the manipulation mode?
For...for
inertia we just turn off the.
Scroll oversee can see this we turn off the translation inertia
...rotation...again just manipulating the
manipulation mode property so very straightforward to do this now let's look
at gesture recognizer so we've rebuilt the same sample shush recognizer
to highlight how if you are using just recognizer some of the differences from doing this in
a framework so it behaves the same way you can translate you can rotate it we can
...axes but the codes a little bit different and the main thing that's different
about the code is that the model for just recognizer is that you receive raw
pointer events and then you take...pointer events and you shovel
in the gesture recognizer and it coughs out events for-you you'll see that the manipulation
...recognizer generates are very similar to what you get from sample the
pointer events will be obviously recognizable you configure just...the same
...the main difference from something like this animal sample showed you is that
your manually feeding the gesture recognizer now gives you a lot of our to you could have a bunch of
just recognizers and feed them often the same input or you can decide which inputs go-to gesture
...maybe you don't want to manipulate the...with planar data
sr with...data and you could look at the type of the pointed and choose to feed it or not
...just recognizer having access to the component gives you more flexibility
so we set up the sample the same way
we the only new thing is that we're creating a windows...you wide-eyed input gesture.
And, we have a little helper class down here manipulation input processor will show
in a second the code to the set
are transforms and
...these axes is pretty much the same source look at how we're setting up.
This helper classmate...so we've
...a couple things we can adjust recognizer hand in the element that we want to manipulate and we hand
and something that's our frame of reference which in this case is sort of apparent most element.
We...gesture recognizer and generate some settings if we go look
at what we're doing with gesture settings here you'll see it looks a lot like the sample.
Area looks...so we're setting x translation
why translation rotation...both of these things we stick it in the gesture settings properties
...configure at the same way you configures animals manipulations
if we go back...main differences
...now listening to some pointer events so we listen to the...pressed...released
and cancel and we set up manipulation handlers here.
Like we did in the previous sample.
Again,
some transform setup that's our setting set-up and
...pointer handlers so when somebody puts their finger down on that
...we're going to start getting
pointer events on it we capture like we were doing and the like
a sliders behind-the-scenes so if your finger starts on the wracked and maybe due to
hire rotating it or maybe you've got scale translations turned on even if your finger
comes slightly off the elemental still send the input to that element
set capture when you come down on it and then we have these process events
...gesture recognizer so you can see here we
call process down and you pass in that...down to gesture recognizer similarly for
removed we pass in a move for released and
...cancel we say process and
up and we release capture in the case that a pointers canceled we tell
the just recognizer just to complete what it's doing reset itself and ...release on the
pointer capture below you get pointer cancel pretty rarely it's sorry.
You get pointer cancel pretty rarely it's used for cases where
the device unexpectedly goes away maybe you had like an external pen tablet and
you unplug...if you are in the middle of a stroke you'd get up pointer cancel event.
We've gotten as far as getting...raw data on a rector getting...data and we've shoveled
...gesture recognizer now just
recognizes working behind the scenes and it figures out what gestures you're seeing so that's when you
start getting these manipulation events so.
Much like the previous sample in manipulation started and in the inertia and complete
...just changing the color and then
in manipulation updated which is like examples manipulation delta events we're.
Doing a couple things.
We're setting the centre again because we still want to build
...point we're setting up
our transform that has the delta and rotation the delta
...translation in both x and y and then that just gets applied
to the element we've already associated delta transform with the element and then sample
...for you so relatively...when we do something like
...one particular axes...works the same way you can just x sorrell
...whatever that specific gesture setting is right so...the x axis for
...soaring out translate...so gesture recognizer works a lot like
this animalmanipulation element or events that you get the main difference is that
you're responsible for creating these things and for handling the
...pointer data in choosing how you feed it to gesture recognizer example does a lot of
that on your behalf but if you want to have more control over you can just recognizer.
...say you're app is.
Super complicated maybe you're doing a billion things on your ui thread or, you know,
maybe you're making some audio academie the
absolute lowest input latency possible that's when you want to use core input.
So, now we're at this...bottom layer of our api surface are stack.
Core inputs gives you your input on another thread it lets you
not be blocked by the ui thread and receive input on some dedicated thread of your
own the way you get a core input is with a structuring...suction panel's example
elements...is really powerful element but it also
asks...from developers you get complete control over inputs and get it on your own thread
even do anything with on the output side though you need to render with direct acts so,
it's a big step up on the output side in terms of what...panel asks from you and
...responsible for everything and...talking panel you also need to now hit test so
we'll show you a sample that recreates the last two that we showed you but,
uses core input...swap...panel's behind-the-scenes
...also I should say using when two-d here this isn't
a talk about renderings we're not going to show you two thousand lines of direct decks code when
two-d is a new api that gives you a universal universal app
...around some of the things like direct rights direct two-d
...of the two-d functionality indirect...when...wraps it up and makes it
...from csharp and provide simplified handlers for things
likes watching panel I've got some...control...so which is really good there's a talk on it too
... simon towers giving at this build so...using that to help on a rendering bull
show you all the input code so we've done two things here we have the same
...that we had before from our sample inoculations and gesture
recognizer sample we have another one that's hooked up to core input and,
we can interactive both these guys but when I start blocking the
...thread you'll see that there's a very different behavior so
we're simulating a very busy app is doing a ton of
...you still want to build interact with it and all we're doing is...making the
...thread sleep for about a hundred milliseconds before it gets to process
...input again but there are apps that see this kind of behavior in the
real-world you want to avoid this and the situations so what show you how you take advantage of
core inputs and get your own thread for input handling?
So, we've got a little bit a setup here...wrecked that
...drawing ...some constance up-front we have some?
Helpers will use for calculating
are transforms and...this is where it gets a little more interesting so we create
a couple things here in this section of we define a couple things here...the section or
she goes first as a swap chain you need a swat chain
...panel canvas swat changes the...the wrapper around the direct
...swap chain class we also create a core independent input...we call this core
input this is the thread that will give you your dedicated
input processing we also create a gesture recognizer that will be using on that
carpet thread to do all our gesture detection I've got a dispatch timer
this just on the ui thread we're going to...is to block...I thread and then we have that manipulation
...processor which was our helper from the previous sample that just creates the gesture recognizer
...in handles it with gesture recognizer so.
We set up our canvas and let's talk about how we set up the swap shame panel we
create a canvas swap...which again is that went to the wrap around dx what chain
...canvas device and then you hand it the number of pixels
wide and tall you want to be in this case we're using the entire window and then you
hand your pixel density so we go and figure out what the logical dpi for the application is hand
it since we're not reciting our app in the sample we're not getting size events if you're doing this for
real and your application you'd want to...windows size event...window and
recreate...swap chain with the new size or if...a dpi event,
for example, some if a user change the systems dpi you'd want to handle that
too so simplifying here for the purposes of the demo and then we just take the
swat chain and stick it in our canvas watching panel canvas...chain panel is the
...two-d wrapper around
...swap...panel mix a little easier to use and then we
draw canvas the very next thing that we were doing in
...setup is initialize input and go look at this and this is where we
actually create the core input and set up some of our handlers so we create
and this line a sort of anonymous a
...action that we're going to run on up thread from the thread pool.
...the very first thing that it does is it asks the swat team panel
for create core independent input source there's just a static factory method on
...panel that coughs up a thread for
you and starts delivering input on it so now
are core input which if you remember was a basically a thread for us now
will start receiving input events we do a couple things there we set up three-pointer events
on...or listing to press...release events
on a thread we create our gesture recognizer on this thread just
organizer has thread affinity if you created on your ui thread but then start feeding it from
another thread you're going to run into problems so we creator gesture recognizer on the same thread that
we're going to be feeding it input we can figure it again just the same way as before so this, you know,
the way we such a settings as exactly like we were doing it before and,
then we set up the same manipulation handlers from gesture...about
before and then we go kick the thread and say hey start processing events so since we call this
will start getting input events on that thread away we go and that's really all we had to do to
set up core input and start getting the events we want...handing them to the gesture recognizer
the next thing that happened in our initialization was we set up our render thread so,
we're just doing this very quickly here again we ask the thread pool to create a
...action for us and all this is going
to do is draw the canvas sixty times a second.
And, when we look at...canvas this is very see some of the powerful...the makes it really
...to draw simple two-d things so like
...rectangle we just create a drawing session off the swap
...we apply our transform that we've been calculating...will show you how
are calculating in our manipulation delta handlers much like
we're calculating the transform for either...animal or the gesture
...sample calculate the same transform this time we apply to our drawing session was
...and that drawing session and tell us what
...to present...called that sixty times per second?
Now one of the...
...you've probably guessed you need to do is because you're getting input on that entire
swat chain and in our sample if you remember the swat
...entire background I need to figure out if I'm interacting with the background
or from interacting with my wrecked here that's hooked up to the slot chain.
So, we have this little helper that
hit tests for us in figures out whether that planar down is actually on an
element we care about one interact with are not so the math here's
so, straightforward we invert the transform we have on our...and apply that
inversion inverted matrix to the point to get everybody in the same
coordinate space and then we just do a simple...
intersection test and figure out whether that finger came down in the rectangle that
were manipulating or not so for poynter events this functions a lot like
you saw in the previous sample we.
Hand gesture recognizer...shoveling raw
pointer data into our configured gesture recognizers recall process down
we get down events we call process move when we get updates from our...data and we
call process...fingers come up gesture recognizer takes care of all the detection behind-the-scenes
...and then starts calling the
manipulation events so these are the same inflation events we saw in the gesture recognizer sample
...doing very similar things here if we look at the updated one
we're just calculating...transform again and we just save it in this
...transform variable which we use on our render thread and
...the drawing session to this is how when you start rotating director start translating
...calculating this new transform for where the wreck should be
and the render thread takes care of harassed so core inputs functions a
lot like how you use just recognizer you configures recognise the same way you feed
...the same way you handle...events the same way the big differences are you're going to be getting
input data for your entire elements
is your sachin panel and you probably need to do a little bit of extra hit testing there if you
had more things you could interact with you would have to hit test each of them figure out
which gesture recognizer associated with those interactive...you want to start feeding the finer data.
...corporate really lets you get down...close to the metals
you can it gives you a lot more control or our a lot more flexibility.
So, a couple other...to be aware of
...api...we have a bunch of stuff we've only not even scratch the surface
...offering for inc and windows ten we have to talks tamar the
...two hundred level talk we'll give you an overview of directing can as...talk
...way deep into the details in the code game pad I think you sauna keynote this morning
...showed using the game pad and being
able to interact with controls and I think it was a video app
so there's two flavors of what you'll get with game pad one game pad will uphold
are promise of all of the built-in controls supporting the various inputs so
you'll get free support for being able to use the d pad on the game pad to navigate between controlling
...the button the select things,
things like that you also get the xbox raw game pad api so-if you want-to
get you analog drumstick data or trigger data or all the
button state things like that you can get that in the universal windows platform
we have great text api coming in...the core text api is that let-you
build word processing apps note-taking apps things like that there's a bunch of device inform factory pies
...talk so much about them today but there's pointer device which you get with any pointer event you
can walk back to advice and find out, you know, it's type and other things there's some capability api
...you check for the presence of different inputs...you want to know if mouse and keyboard or
...you can do that if you want to know of pander touch...attached you can do that there's also some
very simply guys around continuum that tell you what state you're in are you in a more tablet state or in
a more desktop state visual feedback api as you can control mouse cursor is you can turn off
those touch visuals in your app if you wanted something different and then finally I
...the touch targeting api if you are building a custom control
then you may want to use the touch targeting api
is zambia on the frameworks know what the interactive...elements are so, for example,
buttons animal it tells the system...there's a button here has these
bounds the system then can do things like map slot
...sloppy touches on to that button, you know, if you click just offered
missed by a couple pixels while the users probably intending interact with that button the system clean...for
...automatically if you want the system...do that with your custom controls you can use are targeting api
...expose very similar data the system to help make those decisions?
one final thought before wrap-up it's not just about the code it's about how users interact
with your app and the so ui design to you should think about things in
particular for touch, you know, what the size of your controls
are we have recommended sizes to ensure that users can interact with tiny targets
...guidance around white space if you want to know whether you share controls on the edge of your
app or not this and more is covered in
jeff arnold's talk of this nice design talk that talks about how to not only make your...beautiful but make them really
usable for users that's a good segue into related sessions we
...to-ing sessions six eighty one is the search
hundred level introducing directing overview you should definitely turn outline seven-five
...are four hundred level deep dive into thinking platform that's another great talk
...a speech platform talk logo and depth about using the speech platform six
seventy-nine is a sample talk about...ui so you
remember that broad spectrum of windows hardware we talked about how you should be aware of the different inputs and how you
use them across those devices and form factors if you're writing and app that's going
to work on phones and on the surface how we should think about how changes in display size
affect your app to xhtml has a bunch of controls and built-in functionality
around adaptive ui that will help you so transition across different display sizes and six
seventy-nine we'll talk about all that seven three is a talk about continuum
and will help answer questions about what developers need to think about when their building apps...to be aware
...experience and finally six fifty eight the design talk I just mention this will
...apps users love?
...samples pretty much everything I showed you today has a sample and one shape perform up on get
hub today we will take all the code that we put together for this talk and get cleaned up and
get it up on get...
...today...the biggest take away is universal windows platform is going
to drop hundreds of millions of...address of all systems in your lap and the
platform...really easy few to build apps that run on all those devices the apps
the do best will be the ones that do well across the broad set
of from factors that windows runs on and are
...you is that are platform can make easy free to handle input on all those devices
...go forward
...apps hopefully now you have all the tools to build whatever you can envision thank you?
I think we have two minutes for questions
...far questions compton...but,
otherwise I will be at the speakers lounge the insider lounge for the next...and,
happy answer questions there too.
Can use the mikes so the video can capture?
So, if I wanted to use like capture gesture like I'm swiping over
...particular control...capture that or if I draw a circle I want to
be able to tell the difference between the two of those encode
but I use something like that to do it argue that...question
...so something like a circle isn't a gesture that the system
detects natively it's not part of our core interaction language we don't use you know, sort
...circle gesture for anything you could
though detect things likes wipes and then have your own custom detection the
detects a circle and make some decision about those like that's a great place where you could user gesture recognizer
fit some data and see if you got something like a translation or a
...kind of gesture and also be feeding the data to your own just
...that looks for something that's like a circle and then decide what you want to based on that?
...enc recognizer ...question so...
You have looked at the gradual...new at the step stuff so...get the
...once they've been there for a little while I think they're exposed and when age...to be nice if you
...whatever you're calling...under the hood your
...your tuning gesture recognizer...guessing nice if you
doing core input thing you can't use animal...direct...whatever the subroutine
...using a expose so you can use
of yourself that's good feedback you are correct that they're not...today unjust
recognizer you could build those experiences yourself but,
yeah, that's interesting feedback they are exposed at the direct manipulation layer
and in something like example that shows up in scroll viewer or as
cs properties in a web app but if you're using gesture organizer we don't have the
snap points plugged...today?
Cool thanks everybody...see...the speaker latch.